<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mark's space</title><link href="https://kmarc.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://kmarc.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://kmarc.github.io/</id><updated>2019-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Switching to OpenStreetMap from Google Maps</title><link href="https://kmarc.github.io/posts/2019-12-25-switching-to-osm-from-gmaps.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Mark Korondi</name></author><id>tag:kmarc.github.io,2019-12-25:/posts/2019-12-25-switching-to-osm-from-gmaps.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been going on with my "degooglifying" efforts for a while now, however, Google Maps is
something hard to get rid of. It offers so many features, especially when visiting a new
country/city. Now I finally found a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you go, my first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The features …&lt;/h2&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been going on with my "degooglifying" efforts for a while now, however, Google Maps is
something hard to get rid of. It offers so many features, especially when visiting a new
country/city. Now I finally found a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you go, my first blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The features I want to have in the replacement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a handful of them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walking / Cycling navigation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Public transportation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Address / POI search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optionally satellite imagery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all of these both on mobile and my desktop. Of course, you cannot find a solution that
truly replaces Google Maps; however, I found a solution which although consists of multiple
services, apps, and software and is better than Google Maps!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried &lt;a href="https://maps.me/"&gt;Maps.ME&lt;/a&gt;, however, it's very simplistic and doesn't have all the features I wanted. What
especially hurts is the POI search; very difficult to use and get actual results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meet OsmAnd&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, check out &lt;a href="https://osmand.net/"&gt;OsmAnd&lt;/a&gt;'s website. As you can see, it has &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; of features, probably more
than you need. And it's OpenSource; Get it on &lt;a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/net.osmand.plus/"&gt;F-Droid&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.osmand.plus"&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/app/apple-store/id934850257"&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OsmAnd ❤️ Wikipedia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides it has all the features I wanted, the best of all I loved is that it can place Wikipedia
"articles" on the map. For a geek traveler, who wants to know a lot of &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;/em&gt; about a given
place, building, square, region, whatever, I don't know how I could live without this before...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="image-process-article-image" alt="OsmAnd-wikipedia" src="https://kmarc.github.io/pictures/osmand-wikipedia.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the screenshot, the orange circles with a white &lt;code&gt;W&lt;/code&gt; in them represent Wikipedia articles that
were geo-tagged; Clicking on them, a popup opens and you can read the (offline, cached) Wikipedia
article; in this case, about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wat_Manorom"&gt;Manorom Buddhist Temple&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OsmAnd ❤️ Wikivoyage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, now this is the big deal here. For a year now, I am not buying yet another travel book when I
go somewhere; This time I bought &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lonely-Planet-Laos-Travel-Guide-ebook/dp/B06ZZQ8MW7"&gt;Lonely Planet on Kindle&lt;/a&gt;, but that's it. I try to use the
excellent &lt;a href="https://www.wikivoyage.org/"&gt;Wikivoyage&lt;/a&gt; and also contribute back to it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One  of Wikivoyage's  best  features is  that  the  listed "POI"s  are  put  on  a map  (see
&lt;a href="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Luang_Prabang#/maplink/1"&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;). What I did in the past, I printed this map and tried to use Google Maps / Maps.ME
together with the clumsy piece of A4 paper...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="image-process-article-image" alt="OsmAnd-wikivoyage" src="https://kmarc.github.io/pictures/osmand-wikivoyage.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, guess what: OsmAnd can display the POIs from any given Wikivoyage article on an overlay; This
is the best feature so far, and a must-have for travelers. User experience-wise this is more
powerful and convenient than anything Lonely Planet can give you. The Wikivoyage articles are also
downloaded offline, so you can read it while roaming around without network connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Try it and... contribute!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend trying out OsmAnd, it's life-changing. The UI is a bit... strange compared to any other
Android applications, and you can easily get lost in the settings / galore of features. However, at
the same time, it's refreshing. Finally, a software that reminds me of the complex and feature-rich
applications from 15-20 years ago; something that is replaced long ago by dumb smartphone apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rendering of the map does not look fancy; sometimes I would say it's annoyingly flickering.
However, all the extra features balance it out and after all, these features make my life and
travel experience better, aren't they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OsmAnd also makes it super  easy to &lt;strong&gt;edit&lt;/strong&gt; the POIs, so if you find 5  minutes in a coffee shop to
check out  opening hours, phone  numbers, the cuisine  of the bars  and restaurants around,  you can
easily contribute back to the community by editing the POIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also the Wikipedia overlay is only available in the paid version; We are only talking about a couple
dollars per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the smartphone, OsmAnd is a  very good replacement for Google Maps. I expect  it will get even better
in the  future. I  also got  seriously hooked  on OpenStreetMap  now, even  started editing  the map
itself, it's very rewarding, can recommend to everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category><category term="openstreetmap"></category><category term="degooglify"></category></entry></feed>